みなさんのお国にいることは信じられないほど素晴らしい。
残念ながら私たちの文化と
言葉はとても異なっているので、
この気持ちをみなさんの言葉で伝えることは
不可能ですし、私の母語で私の気持ちを伝えても
みなさんは理解できないでしょう。
私の母語はイタリア語なので、
自己紹介は数語でできてしまいます。
私の言葉だと
"Buonasera, lo sono Italo Vignoli."
これは私たちの言葉がみなさんのものといかに
異なっているかを示していますが、
フリー／オープンソースソフトウェアが独特なのは
異なる文化や背景を持っていても
完全に透明性のあるやり方で
ともに活動することができることだと、私は考えます。
昨日の夕食会では、少なくとも二つか三つの大陸からの
参加者がいましたが、なにか違いを感じるということは
ありませんでした。
宗教についてもイスラム教徒、キリスト教徒、
仏教徒、そしてたぶんアジアならではの
異なる宗教の人もいましたが、
これもまた私たちの間には障壁には
ならなかったと思います。
私はこの場でみなさんにお話できることを誇らしく
思います。TDFのコアメンバーがみなさんの国を訪問
することはこれが最後ではないと希望します。
もし可能ならみなさんもぜひヨーロッパを訪ねてください。
そのときはぜひ私たちに連絡をください。
最高のヨーロッパをお見せしますよ。
たぶん旅行ってわけではない……とは、思います。
さて、はじめにいくつかの地図から始めたいと思います。
ご存知の方も多いかもしれませんが
私の専門は地理で、私は地理学者なんです。
技術とソフトウェアの世界にいるのは単なる偶然です。
ついでにいえば、
地理学者で毎月給料を得るのは難しいという
事実もあります。
そんなわけでいくつかの地図から始めます。何人かの
かたはすでにご覧になったかもしれないですが、
オープンソースソフトウェアへの投資が
足りていないことが世界の不均衡を作っているということを
示すものです。さて、これは
みなさんご存知の、典型的な地図です。
各国はその面積で表現されています。
さて、もちろん、日本は私の国、
これが私の国ですが、
と、だいたい同じか、ちょっと大きいですが、
それでもすごく大きくはないですね。
人口に切り替えてみましょう。そうすると
日本はイタリアよりもだいぶ大きくなることが
おわかりでしょう。これはイタリア人よりも日本人のほうが
多いからですが、たとえばインド、例えば中国、
なんと大きいのでしょう。とても沢山の人が住んでいる
からです。そして南米はなんと小さいか、
カナダはなんと小さいか。大きな国なのに。
では興味深いものに行きましょう。
ソフトウェアライセンスの輸出量です。いいですか。
すごく巨大な国がありますね。誰もがご存知でしょうから、
名前は言わなくてもいいでしょうか。
これはアイルランドです。ヨーロッパにおいてアイルランドは、
アメリカとヨーロッパの橋渡しになっているのです。
ですからヨーロッパの巨大企業、アメリカの巨大企業は
アイルランドにオフィスを持って、自身のソフトウェアを
輸入し、それをヨーロッパ全土に
輸出しているのです。
正直なところ税金がとっても安いからです。
この「泡」はなんだろうと考えているかもしれません。
これはスリナムです。スリナムは南米の
とっても小さな国で、南米において
アイルランドと似た機能を果たしています。
昔のオランダの植民地で、税率は4%です。
なのでもちろん、MicrosoftやOracleはスリナムに
彼らのソフトウェアを出荷し、
スリナムから南米の別の国に輸出しているのです。
さて、大変にアンバランスですね。
アフリカはどこにありますか。みなさんの国はどこでしょう。
私が言いたいのは、みなさんの国は世界から、そう世界から
消えてしまっているということで、これは不幸な
状況だということです。アメリカにソフトウェア
開発をするなといいたいわけではなく、
もっとバランスのとれた状況にしたいと言っているのです。
では輸入を見てみましょう。
輸入は輸出のまったく反対です。
日本がとっても大きいのがわかりますね。
イタリアも大きいです。アイルランドは、輸出のために
ソフトウェアを沢山輸入しているので
大きいです。
ではアメリカがどこにあるかを教えますね。
メキシコとカナダのあいだにあるこの1ピクセルの線です。
ソフトウェアラインセンスの輸入においては、
彼らは基本的には存在しないということで、
ちょっと考えて想像してみてください。
通常はそれぞれの地域で、ぜんぶが地域でではないにせよ
少なくとも一部は地域で開発されることが一般的な、
フリーソフトウェアがもっと広まっていたらどうなるか。
これが、私たちがプロジェクトを始めたときに
置かれていた状況です。
これは私たちの紙飛行機で、2010年にプロジェクトを
はじめ、2020年にはこう、と夢見てきたものです。
2億のユーザーを持ちたい、ソフトウェア業界に
食い込みたい。
最初の想定と比較すると、私たちはすでに目標を
達成したと言えると思いますが、
理想とする目標には
未だ距離があります。
私たちにはOpenOffice.orgの10年にわたる
資産があります。
LibreOfficeプロジェクトを始めた多くの人たちは
OpenOfficeコミュニティで活発に活動していました。
日本でも、何人かは過去に活発で、
何人かはもうプロジェクトから離れ、
何人かはもはや活発ではないと知っていますが、
プロジェクト開始時の私たちのアイディアは
とても強固な歴史の上に築かれました。私たちの背景は強固です。
OpenOfficeは1984年に誕生しました。
Marco Börriesが最初のプロダクトを作り
それをリリースしたときまで歴史を遡るなら、
私たちは30年か、40年近い歴史を
持っているということになるのです。
OpenOfficeは2000に始まり、
このプロジェクトの歴史において、
ずっと苦闘してきて、LibreOfficeになってから
解決した複数の問題がありました。
たとえば、これは2000年のOpenOfficeです。
基本的なコードとリポジトリがこうでした。
そして2005年のこと、たくさんの楽しい機能を
開発したので、
OpenOfficeはちょっと太ってきました。
2006年、リヨンのカンファレンスにて、
OpenOfficeガイドによるプレゼンがあり、
彼らは「わかったよ、コミュニティが
ある分野では動きようがないんだよね。
だからコードの複雑さを減らすことにするよ」これは結局
できずじまいで、LibreOfficeにより改善されました。
私たちはパッチの扱いも改善しました。この当時、
吉田浩平さんによる有名なパッチ、
マージされるまで28ヶ月も放置されていました。
ブランチに放置されて28ヶ月もそのままなんて、
まったく受け入れることができません。
幸いなことにこのパッチは実に先進的で、
28ヶ月後でも意味があるものでしたが、
技術の世界で28ヶ月といえば一世代です。
それから、初心者のメンタリング、これも
LibreOfficeでちゃんとやるように
なったものです。
さて、2009年のOracleによるSunの買収まで急ぎましょう。
このときコミュニティメンバーはすでにSunが
この状況をどう扱うかについて取り残されていたので、
OpenOfficeがちゃんと扱えていなかったことを
一新するためにフォークするには今が正しいときだと
急いで決断し、実行に移しました。
OpenOfficeはここで、現実問題として
OracleがOpenOfficeをやめるリスクはとても大きく、
結果として私たちは正しく、彼らはやめてしまったのですが、
私たちのほとんどはLibreOfficeとなり、
ご存知のとおり、今日では、
LibreOfficeは開発の軌跡となって、
10年近くものあいだリリースされ続け、
通常、年2回のメジャーリリース、
毎月か1.5ヶ月ごとのマイナーリリースをしてきて、
プロダクトはずっとメンテされ続けてきたのです。
私たちの宗教の言葉で「最後の晩餐」という
言葉がありますが、この状況とは似ていないため、
私たちは「最初の晩餐」というほうがよいですが、
それが2010年9月2日、ブタペストで行われました。
基本的にはLibreOfficeプロジェクトを
創設した人たちでしたが、
プロジェクトを取り巻く人たち、たとえば公証人も
その一人ですが、も一緒でした。
ともかく参加者は、この新しいプロジェクトを
どうやったら一緒に進められるかを真剣に議論しました。
何人かはみなさんもご存知かもしれません。これはFlorian Effenberger
これはChris Nowak、LibreOfficeの色として
緑を選び、デザインを作った人です。その後子どもが生まれ、
仕事を変えたためプロジェクトからは
離れましたが、それでも彼の貢献は
土台となるものです。フランスからCharles Schulz、
今でも関わっています。Kendy、あるいはJan Holešovský、
Kendyのほうが簡単ですね。Thorsten Behrens、
Michael Meeks、Caolán McNamara、
これは私、Sophie、彼の名前は覚えてないですね、
いずれにせよこのあと仕事が変わりましたが、
(会場のLothar氏から補足) ああ、そうだ。Cor Nouws、
Olivier Hallot、コペンハーゲンからLeif Lodahl。
私たちがフォークをしたのです。
そしてこれ、告知文を作って、2020年に目標を置いたのです。
来年ですね。
今は道中、9年目ということになります。
そしてこれはそれからのフォークの歴史です。
ご存知のとおり、Apache OpenOfficeがあります。
IBMがフリーソフトウェアプロダクトと競合するような
プロダクトを選んだのは残念なストーリーですが、
この会社は、少なくともヨーロッパでは、
日本でのことはわからないですが、少なくともヨーロッパと
アメリカでは、この会社はコミュニティを好いてはおらず、
特にコミュニティメンバー、
私のような、を嫌っていたのです。
私は、これはなにか間違っているぞと思ったときには
とても単刀直入になるほうで、
間違っているぞと伝えます。
繰り返しますが、Sunの何年かのやり方はなにか間違って
いて、彼らは私の透明性をあまりありがたくは思って
いなかったようです。
そして、私たちはパラダイムを引っくり返しました。
これはOpenOfficeです。企業がプロジェクトを守ります。
雨が降ったとき、傘の下にいる人は濡れずにすみますが、
傘の下にいなければ濡れてしまいます。
私たちは傘を引っくり返しました。これはサラダボウル
のコンセプトです。アメリカでは、
サラダの材料があったとき、
それをボウルに入れてよくかき混ぜれば、
サラダはおいしくなるとされます。
味がよりよくなるのです。
少なくとも私の国では、こんなふうにいいます。
ボートに一緒に乗ったら全員が同じ方向に
漕がなくちゃいけない。
たぶんヨーロッパの他の国でも似たような言い方を
すると思います。アジアのみなさんが
こんな感じのたとえを用いるかはわかりませんが、
コンセプトはシンプルです。コミュニティがこっちに行くと
決めたら、みんなは貢献を提供する活力を得られるのです。
これは私たちのホームページ、
最初のホームページで、創立の
規範がかいてあります: コピーレフトなライセンス、
今はLGPLからMPLに移行しました。
貢献者同意（contributor agreement）をやらない、
実力主義、コミュニティによるガバナンス、
ベンダーからの独立。
私たちの約款では、取締役会では、ある企業の代表者となる
投票権が30%を越えてはならないとなっています。
それから、私たちがプロジェクトを立ち上げたとき、
それを見ていた多くの人がOracleへの抗議だと
いいましたが、そうではありません。
Oracleへの抗議ではないのです、
なにか新しいものを作るためのプロジェクトなのです。
私たちがOracleに対する刺客である、だから
みなさんにもOracleを刺してほしい、としている
という記事が出たことがありましたが、
それは完全に間違いです。
私たちはフリーソフトウェア、
利用の自由、ドキュメントの自由、オープンな標準、
というセットを広めたいのです。もちろん、
LibreOfficeを開発します。
もう一つのプロジェクトもあり、Document Liberationです。
ドキュメントのインポート・エクスポートを行うフィルターを扱います。
ここにいくつか数字があります。
私たちには206人のメンバーがいて、
そして……ところで、ここにいるみなさんの中で、
TDFのメンバーでない人がいることを私は知っています。
そして、来週末までには、
ここにいるみなさんの中でTDFメンバーではない人たちからの
メンバー応募が届くと期待しています。
メンバーシップ委員会の議長は親しい友人で、
ともにイタリア人で、
彼はGabriele Ponzoというのですが、
彼に、誰が応募を送ってきて誰が送っていないかを
教えてくれるように言っておきます。
私はみなさんがどこにいるのか知っているのですから……。
いや、本当ではないですが、
真面目に考えてくださいよ。
さて、私たちの主な資産は開発者です。
アジアにはとても沢山開発者がいるとはいえなくて、
もっと増えることを願っています。
開発者は貴重なので、みなさんありがとうございます。
開発者なしではプロジェクトを終わらせることはできません。
プロダクトが存在しなくなってしまうからです。
実際には、素晴らしいプロダクトが存在します。
単に仲間内で使うだけでなく、
政府でも使える、自信をもって、政府に勧めることが
できます。
なぜなら、いかなるプロプライエタリなソフトウェアを
置き換えることで、それを使う人々に利点をもたらす
ことができるプロダクトを持っているわけですから。
これは開発者の数です。
濃い緑色は昔からの開発者で、
すでにプロジェクトに参加している人たちを刺します。
しかしこのグラフは2010年から2016年の終わりまでしか
ないことがおわかりでしょう。
その時点で数えるのをやめたのです。
何人かから批判を受けたからです。いわく、
こんなことをしたら開発者を集められない、
開発者が離れてしまう、と。
だから私たちは開発者を好きじゃないんですが、
これは事実で、問題解決に取り組んだ
開発者を1200人近くまで数えたところで、
数を数えるのをやめました。
理屈が通らないからです。
これに置き換わる図をお見せしたいと思います。
有給か無給かによらない、でもほとんどが企業により
給料が支払われている「コア」開発者が40人ほど
います。彼らはより強固な開発をします。
また何人かの「一般的」開発者がいて、
ここにも一般的開発者は何人かいるかと思いますが、
重要な開発をしています。
それから「一時的」開発者。
一時的開発者はだいたい毎年入れ替わります。
結論として、だいたい年に300人ぐらいの開発者が
いることになり、
これはプロダクトが強固なバックグラウンドを持っている
ということを示します。
これは2019年のコミット数です。
見て取れるように、もちろん、土曜日、日曜日、
それぞれの休暇がありますが、
とてもしっかりしています。これは
LibreOffice 6.2のリリース告知の直前です。
これは、そう、もちろん、
リリース告知の前後は活動がスパイクするのです。
これは組織別の貢献数です。
多くの開発者が企業に雇用されています。
これはCollaboraによるパッチ、
これはRed Hatのもの、unknownは
ボランティアを呼ぶよい呼び方ではないですが、
彼らは企業の後援を受けておらず、
なので私たちは「unknown」という言葉を使いますが、
それからCIB、TDFはTDFによって雇用されている人たち、
それから他の組織によるちょっとした機会もあります。
このスライドで見て取れる大事なことは、
50%を超えるような活動をしている
単独の企業または組織は存在しないということです。
これはプロジェクトの推進力で、
なぜならもし50%をやっている組織がいなくなったら、
プロジェクトを生きたまま続けることはできなくなって
しまうからです。
そしてこれは私たちの4つの開発サイクルです。
3.3から始まりましたが、このときは「掃除」と呼ばれていました。
4.xはコードのリファクタリング、すでにプロダクトには
入っているけれども実際には最適化されていないコードの
再開発を行いました。次の作業はユーザーインターフェイスで、
ユーザーインターフェイスの改善は今でも続いていますが、
現実として私たちは今6.xで、
モバイルアプリケーションについては活発であるとは
言えないとはいえ、LibreOfficeは、
すべてのプラットフォームで動作する
唯一のフリーのオフィスソフトなのです。
すべてというのは、Windows、macOS、Linux、
そしてクラウドとモバイルを指しています。
Microsoft Officeに近いところにいる
唯一の存在で、Microsoft OfficeはLinux版を
持っていないからですが、LibreOffice以外は、
モバイルまたはその他のものも、
クラウド版は存在しなくて、私たちには
LibreOffice Onlineがあり、
今日もいくつか発表がありましたが、
もちろん、とても大事なことは、私たちは
技術を可能にする「エンジン」を提供しているので、
インフラを提供しているわけではないと人々に
説明すべきことです。
インフラは非営利団体が担うにはコストが
見合わないからです。
そして私たちはとてもよい品質を保っています。
コードを綺麗に保つ週次のサービスである
Coverity Scanを利用しており、
GoogleによるOSS-Fuzzも使っていて、
その他コードの品質を高めることができるすべての
ツールを利用しています。
Coverity Scanのレポートを見れば、
LibreOfficeは1,000行あたりの
問題数がたぶん最も少ないオフィスソフトで
あることを知ることができます。
たとえばFirefoxや、
たとえばThunderbirdのように、
とても安定したsふとであると考えられているものよりも
低い件数です。
もちろん、これはLibreOfficeが
バグがないソフトウェアであるということを意味しません。
バグがないソフトウェアは存在し得ないです。
しかし私たちはとても強固なコード基盤を持っています。
そしてコミュニティも、開発者と同じく強力な資産です。
コミュニティは2番目に大事です。なぜなら、
もし開発者がいなければ、
プロダクトは手にはいりません。
しかしもしコミュニティがなかったら、
各国語版はできないですし、それぞれの地域の
マーケットに向けてのプロモーションも行えません。
なのでコミュニティは素晴らしいです。
そして我々みんな、自身がその一部であることを
誇りに思うべきです。
そしてコミュニティの地図です。ナイジェリアがなくて
すみません、急いで追加します。
すべての地域でコミュニティが存在するかを
知ることは不可能なので、最善の推測として
ネットワーク越しの情報を用いているのです。
もちろん、アフリカは私たちfoundationにとって
最優先の地域です。
なぜならこの大陸では、ソフトウェアのニーズが
とてもたくさんあるのに対して、
問題としては文化的に現実を説明するのが
難しいことですが、
ともかくみなさんの国を見て取れます。
アメリカ大陸、中央アメリカにはコミュニティが
あると思っていますが、
他の国のようにその証拠が見当たらないのですが、
アジアでは概ねどの国にもコミュニティがあります。
そしてコミュニティが存在しているように
見えない国を開発していく、
そしてコミュニティが他の国ほどのレベルに
達していない国も開発していくことが大事です。
これはインドのコミュニティのレベルを
どう上げていくかを
私たちが議論していることを
言っているわけです。それから私は、
中国もまた重要だと思っています。
幸いなことにコミュニティには
中国語が話せる人たちがいます。台湾人ですが、
同じ言語が喋れるということではそうです。
これはもちろん大きな助けになります。
中国コミュニティについてはすでに基礎があるということです。
インドは、複雑な国だと思っています。
とても大きく、人口が多く、
言語もたくさんあります。なので
とても難しいです。
そして、このようなカンファレンスに参加することは
とても大事です。なぜなら自分たちの外のコミュニティが
どう活動しているか、多くを学べるからです。
ヨーロッパはとても小さいです。
continent is a smaller than China's
moral dimension is probably smaller than
Australia. And this is a is a continent
so of course in in Europe where the
project was born community is really
looks alike in every country the
differences are really minor apart from
languages. But differences were in the
way you develop the community are very
small. While the community works in
different ways in your geographies just
because we have very strong but very
different cultures and we respect all
the cultures I was in Indonesia last
year and I think that the Indonesians
have done a wonderful work in growing
the community, they started two years and
a half three years ago but now they have
a community as is self-sustaining, they
are organizing events local events, they
are attracting more people because of
course in a community you have people
that come in go and you cannot back on
the fact that people is staying here forever.
And this is the activity of the community
these are
just to give you, this is the core, these
are the regular people, and these are the
casual people, this is based just on the
commit or the number of emails that are
sent this is the dashboard of the
document foundation you can access it at
the dashboard.documentfoundation.org.
So you can check it for
yourself and you can filter the data
to see according to your interests.
And of course, last asset is LibreOffice,
open source software is is now adopted by the
majority but still we have to do a lot
to make people aware about open source
software. If we look at Google Trends
LibreOffice is this one, so this at last 12
months, Brazil is the country
where most research are coming from, but
of course, if we look at the more details
this is very general is Google Trends so
it's based on searche,s but if we look at
other measurement methods for instance,
in in Asia
you see Japan having probably the larger
share
and I will show the the slide about Asia
in a few minutes.
User base estimate, as I said we are
estimating around 200 million users, so
this is more or less how we estimate the
number, so there are between 2 and 3
billion users, PC users, we say that we
have 100 percent of Desktop Linux, maybe
it's not 100 that is 99.9.
We have 10% of desktop Windows,
10 percent of desktop macOS, so if you
sum all the figure is 236 million and
we say, okay we are conservative, we say
we have 200 million is probably 100
million are unique users, the other 100
million are using also another software
so they may be using Microsoft Office or
other office suites or other specific
software.
We provide two versions fresh versus still
we deliberately do not use
the word stable, because the reality is
that they are both stable, but they need
let's say that one is newer than the
other or if you want the Still is the
more tested by users, of course when we
suggest which version to use, we usually
suggest the older one, not because not
because the newer one creates issues, but
because you never know who are the users
so it's better to start with a more
tested version and then if necessary
move to the next one, but instead of the
opposite.
And this is more or less gives you the numbers,
remember that LibreOffice is still we have LTS options.
so there are two companies they are both sitting
on the advisory board, they provide the LTS
version so if you meet a government or
corporation
that wants to get a product that is
optimized for their need, they are not
getting a better product, they get a
brother that is optimized, so they have
support they have back porting of
patches, for instance, we... we do not back
port patches over nine months so when
when the software is nine month old you
you don't get any any security patch any more.
While on LTS version, you
get security patches back ported forfive years.
So let's say that you could
update the software after five years,
instead of doing it every six nine months.
That can be an issue in some
cases.
This is LibreOffice Online Writer,
this is LibreOffice Online Calc.
They work... they work amazingly well they're
solid and they save ODF
and ODF is important.
What can we do in the future.
In the future we can together, but
only we do that together we can really
build a global ecosystem and
contributing means sharing it's we are
all, and let me make a note about the
language here. Unfortunately we don't
speak the same language all over the
world. This is in one sense a pity
because we have communication issues but
the beauty because each language
represents our culture. So we are forced
to use English as a kind of global
language, English is not my native
language, I'm a decent English speaker
but English is not my native language.
With my wife, she's there,
mystic Italian we don't speak English
within ourselves. So I totally understand
and the effort that you make looking how
you've run your language. The effort that
you make it's amazing to speak English
that is based on our Western way of
writing, so we are amazed by the fact
that you are managed to speak such a
line of language, but don't be shy.
We want to, if you know three words of
English, use those three words of English.
We want to understand you. Don't don't
consider English as a barrier. It is not.
if necessary it's that to do signs, we
Italians are very good at dancing on the
floor, so the same, because that you're
communicating is more important than
judging the others on language skills.
And let's look at a few numbers on Asia.
So this... this is the visits to the download page.
I can give you this is two other
but this is important because it's visits
to download page, so these are the continent.
As you can see, Europe is still
quite high, Asia is still is divided in
East Asia, Central Asia. We have to
improve because still Europe and North
America are still they have they rely on share.
These are from Asia area
so you have East Asia, Central Asia, South
Asia, Southeast Asia, and Western Asia.
Of course, this probably tells you a lot
more than what it tells to me because
you know the reality of your continent.
And these are the countries. Of course I
have to create an others because there
is a very long tail of countries, but yes,
India, then after Japan and Indonesia then
you have China, Turkey, Philippines, Taiwan
Thailand, South Korea, Saudi Arabia,
Malaysia, Hong Kong, Vietnam, Pakistan,
Singapore, Israel and the other one are 6%.
As you can see, there are
unbalance in term of so this does not
reflect them the potential number of
users of your countries, of course and
people see Japan here but Japan has one
tenth of the inhabitants of India, so India
should have a lot more downloads than Japan,
nothing mean don't stop downloading you
let's have the Indians increasing the
downloads
And that's like what this guy,
because I am an old man, so most of the
times I'm the oldest thing in in the
building I don't know if I'm the oldest
here because I'm not able to judge you
as I would be able to judge a European
but I'm 65 so I don't think there are
many younger people than me and I think
"you're never
too old to have another goal and to
dream a new dream," so I want to stay here
for years again to help younger people
to grow up in the community, I think that
it's very important for someone that has
experience to transfer the experience to
the younger people. So my dream is, this
is FOSS today, this is people that know
free and open-source software these are
those that use, but they in many case
they use but they don't know, for
instance, many use VLC on their mobile
phones and they don't think is free
software. And these are the people that
refuse, and my dream is tomorrow to say
these are people that know these are the
people that use and these are the people
that refuse this mean we cannot get rid
of those unfortunately, and that's all
for my part of the speech, and there is
Lothar now that will add a few important
remarks about certification how to build
a business also around LibreOffice.
So, thank you very much.
Before i introduce myself, I think so tropical I want to
tell you that I have all three
challenges, the first one is it's my
first stay in Asia in my life, and I'm
very wanted to be here in the LibreOffice Conference Asia,
and the second
one is it's also the first time in my
life that I present my presentation and
have used to to presentation before my
wife, so please be kind with touch nervous.
And the third one is to speak after
Italo, it's... it's a challenge, it's a
challenge because he's so so good in
making presentations and I won't stress
you too much I will hurry up a little
bit to join the six o'clock.
So, first of all, let's have a look a little bit on
the business side,
I want to speak a little bit about certifying
as a LibreOffice professional,
and why this is a win-win-win situation
for the community,
and perhaps that we have a few words to myself,
this is all formal stuff
that as Italo mentioned
the history of StarOffice and OpenOffice,
My company .riess applications was the
first migration partner of some in
Europe so we have done the first one of
the first migration project in the early
2000s it was 2001 or something about this that
we have worked[?]
together with the staff of Sun and spoke
with them about how can we bring OpenOffice, StarOffice then OpenOffice
to professional users as the deployment
in an professional environment.
And this is now 7 or 8 years we have changed the
product LibreOffice, so this is the
track records I have in business with an
allowance open opposite[?] LibreOffice.
So, let me focus on the community and I
wanted to bring in a part of the
community in which is not always
recognized but which we all know that it
is a very important part of the
community,
it's the third group of stakeholder it's
the eco systems around the product we have.
the first group first for most all
users around them, they are private, they
are professional, even if they use LibreOffice offline as we know everybody and
the new ones since few years Online, and
prefers Online their first times, and the
second one is the computer team, often
spoke about the community, it's the
participants to develop the product
so everybody who brings in some
contributions to the product is a man
that we speak with community, yes,
also the ecosystem which is needed to
guarantee the support the professional
support and services for these professional
environments what we want to discuss.
So, as we start conversation for thinking
about business, thinking about business
in was in Asia, there wasn't the question
how do we get business around LibreOffice,
is it like the genesis from dust coming out,
perhaps Italo is saying "bang!" and
there are some big migration projects to
be progress with professional
deployments and checking who doing
this ecosystem and everything is
fine for the next hundreds of years.
No, we all know I don't want to to have any
religious feelings by that we all know and
this is not the kind or the way it will happen.
So what could be the way it pretends? and
this is what I want to mention in this
talk what brings LibreOffice and some
kind of community, some kind of ecosystems, some kind of projects...
to a very wise one where we have chicken,
we have egg, and
growing up more and more over the time,
and the question is what are the
catalysts, what are the criterias, to
grow that up to have a vital ecosystem
around LibreOffice.
As I recap my slides, this
morning I was a little bit concerned
about this slide. Because, to bring in, here in
Asia, the role model of Europe in this
case Germany,
I felt a little bit that this is
misplaced. Why? Well, ecosystem with and
around LibreOffice is services. it's most
part services support and what we
discovered the last last two days is
that the cultural services here in Asia
as a lot higher and better and that we
have in Europe, so I'm feeling a little
bit concerned to bringing this example
how how it can works, but perhaps we can
take the catalysts I've marked them in
green, LibreOffice green, color which are the
cafeterias which I think could be
catalysts for bringing up more
business world.
So let's have a look at what has
happened in Germany. There were some
anchor persons and some local community
there which starts doing some business.
So it's all about you and me ,there
must be some person who say "yes, we do it,"
and that's very very important.
In the German case, little mentioned some names,
Thomas Jacqueline, Florian, as well as Thorsten,
and our persons. [???] enough or not enough[?],
an anchor company who care about
the products, it was in the early stage
StarDivision, afterwards it was Sun, I
have talked with Michael Bemmer around these, all these community issues,
see it as good or bad, catalysts
that was good anchor companies want to make business with them.
Third one, the lighthouse projects. Not
many projects, but I remember that in the
early 2000s, I was talking to the
city of Munich about the whole migration
to Linux and this stage of OpenOffice, and
that it's rather the years that they
decide to do that. So some lighthouse
projects are important that other which
are thinking about to migrate see that
there are some role models for it.
Especially in our case of public has
administration's who were thinking about
turning away from Microsoft Office to LibreOffice, and
why did then because there was a
depression in the ecosystem. There was
somewhere a cost sensitivity, which we
heard in all over topside works, today
the cost sensitive all about license
costs, awareness about vender lock-in,
with long consequences also costs
arguments.
And the way to support Open Document Format, technical issue to come to to
peel the side of this vendor lock-in. So
this this were catalysts there were some
people as mentions besides Sun who
want to make business bridge who some
services support for for the software
and afterwards
we developed these certifying process
for acknowledge some companies, some
people and these companies that they do
a qualified service for this product.
And this is the only thing, the only thing
you see the others become you can check
for for Asia, I think there are some
anchor persons here the rule for Asia who
are promoting this product like Franklin,
like Shinji here in Japan, like Alice,
sorry to be not mentioned everybody, but
there are anchor persons and the local
community, who is couple of do that. I think collect some anchor
companies, awesome lighthouse projects as
as CTC from Taiwan, Fans from
Indonesia and of us we heard today which
are it could be the lighthouse projects
as catalyst is here to the ecosystem in Asia.
I don't know if there is something
like a kind of depression in Asia, but I
know and you have mentioned in the talks
there's a costs
and the sensitivity from the lock-in
issue in Asia, so what we can do from Europe
or from all the community, the ecosystem
community could help you at least certification.
Let me give just short
introduction to this certifying
LibreOffice certifying proces.
If it were interesting I tell you that we have
tomorrow these business workshops and
registration so asked me questions about
that tomorrow that I is become an accent
explain the whole process in this few
minutes but just a few words.
There are four profiles for... we think
four profiles for certifying.
There are professional certified developers,
there are professional migration consultants, theer are trainers, professional trainers, with the own profiles,
and perhaps somewhere in the future
we will have an own profile for
certified supports consultants, but we
cover this supports profile I think a
part of the migration and the
part of the trainer skills.
And this is... these are the profiles about the kind of
process to get certified . The profile of
development is levels slightly different
the other two. Developers are invited by
the engineering steering committee so
they are recognized for giving
contributions to the source code and if
you have done some of these
contributions they recognize you as a
developer who can master the code, and
then you will be invited and if you want
to be listed as certified developer, and
if you say yes you will be listed.
Quite different is the certification for
migration and training to be sure in the
process we certify people, not companies,
and as a consultant for migration or as
a trainer you should have some
experience in this area for training or
for migrating to LibreOffice, then you
should show these experience, for example
with some documents, to the committee
applicate to to this certifying role,
with these documents and it will be
reviewed by the committee and if it is
acknowledged that it seems to be like
little bit experienced in this area, you
get divided to do such a registration
which we are doing tomorrow here... and if
the committee of reviewers, normally
three or four, all of these committees and yes
we trust these quality of service of
this person who gets certified.
So why it is chocolates[?], why is this
helping, why is this a win-win-win-win
in the community from the stakeholders.
So I think it's easy to
understand out of the customer side of a
professional user side, it's good to have
suction such contracts such a list you
if you need such a certified service
where you can have contact persons where
you have you can ask and you know that
they are used with trust from the
community. So mainly the customer, the
users are gaining the quality of
services some of these certification.
The community everybody who is in the
contribution truth. Typical win element is that we get out of
these certified people certainly and
I believe us how we can develop the product
heads, especially ahead in in the way for
using it in professional environments.
Integration issues, compatibility issues,
and so on.
And the third poem that win is typically
for applicants, because
you ask certified people listed in
an official list of TDF, on LibreOffice online
websites, where everybody can see that
you are certified migrator, certified trainer,
or something like this.
And certainly the witness working in such an awesome community, we enjoy with you.
So... Doumo Arigato!
Okay, it's six o'clock so I mean if you have questions
and take part tomorrow come to me come
to Italo and we will help you with this.
Thank you very much!